all right
[Music]
should doctors recommend their patients
do yoga as you've seen in my last videos
the difficulties associated with
recommending yoga stem from the low
quality of scientific evidence available
regarding its effects oddly this lack of
evidence is partly due to a common
failure among researchers to Define what
they actually study they just say yoga
without defining what they mean
and different types of Yoga differ
greatly in what they demand in terms of
physical strength depth of meditation
breathing control and spiritual
component yet it's very common for
reports of studies not to Define which
type they use this not only makes it
hard to compare results between studies
it also makes it very hard to translate
any findings to the bedside when
counseling patients
yoga is broadly defined as a mind-body
practice composed of physical postures
breathing techniques and meditation and
so if researchers say they put yoga to
the test you'd assume all three
components would be present however some
studies use meditation only in call it
yoga with no postures or breathing
others only examine breathing exercises
and call it yoga others consider yoga
only postures and still others say
they're studying forms of yoga without
any of the three components and so if a
study shows no benefit does that really
mean yoga as commonly practiced didn't
help and if a study does show benefit
what exactly do you tell patients to do
to achieve it
we can take some comfort in the fact
that a review entitled is One Yoga style
better than another attempted to compare
the effects of the more than 50
different yoga styles used in hundreds
of Trials and they concluded that there
was no apparent winner in terms of
whether the results turned out positive
so to a certain extent they may be
interchangeable
I've talked about the need to have
active control to see if there's some
benefit to yoga Beyond just the exercise
component but such controls may still
not deal with confounders such as
socialization yoga usually involves
going to classes so you can imagine if
you were studying the effects of yoga on
something like depression I mean does
Breaking routine getting out and meeting
other people have any effect independent
of the yoga sadly for depression yoga
doesn't even seem to have a benefit
compared to doing nothing yoga does
appear to be helpful with anxiety but
not for people anxious to the extent
that they're actually diagnosed with an
anxiety disorder and all the anxiety
benefit from yoga appears to just be
from the physical activity since there
appears to be no benefit compared to
other types of exercise
so unfortunately yoga does not appear to
be effective for mood and anxiety
disorders
a review on the effects of yoga on
depressive symptoms in people with
mental disorders in general including
conditions like PTSD or schizophrenia
found no significant effect compared to
things like social support that offer
the same kind of attention or to doing
nothing but did find an effect compared
to so-called wait list controls see
unlike in studies of drug effects where
Placebo sugar pill is relatively
straightforward selection of a control
condition is much more complex for
Behavioral interventions like yoga
and one common solution is a passive
control such as a wait list basically
people are randomized to either yoga or
onto a waitlist where they'll still get
yoga but have to wait a while now that's
better than having no control group at
all since it still controls for the
passage of time meaning whether or not
your condition would have just gotten
better naturally on its own but doesn't
really control for the placebo effect
right if instead you were just told you
were entering a study to see if some
exercises may help and then unbeknownst
to you randomized to do yoga versus some
sort of sham yoga then you would have
the same kind of expectation either way
but if you know going into it you're
going to get yoga now which may help or
yoga in six months and you end up in the
wait list control this may spuriously
amplify the difference in treatment
effect because people assigned to the
wait list may expect to not get better
without active treatment
for example here's a study for yoga on
urinary incontinence women were
randomized to six weeks of yoga or a
weightless control group after six weeks
the incontinence frequency decreased by
70 percent in the yoga therapy versus
only 13 fewer episodes in the control
group but it's possible that the women
in the yoga group reported some benefits
due to what's called an expectation bias
because they expected yoga to be helpful
So based on the body of evidence one
might say there's insufficient good
quality evidence to judge whether yoga
is useful for women with urinary
incontinence
but what we'd like to see are studies
comparing yoga to time and attention
control interventions some alternative
to yoga that entail the same amount of
time and attention so people don't even
know they're in a control group
now the question arises who cares if the
benefits from a yoga intervention are
due to the placebo effect or expectation
bias a benefit is a benefit as long as
people are getting better who cares but
it would be nice to know if yoga really
helps or not and here we go women with
urinary incontinence were randomly
assigned to yoga group or to a rigorous
time and attention control group
involving non-specific muscle stretching
and strengthening exercises
there are two different types of urinary
incontinence urgency incontinence
defined as an involuntary loss of urine
associated with a sudden strong desire
to urinate or stress incontinence where
an activity such as sneezing triggers an
involuntary leak
three months of yoga didn't seem to
significantly help overall incontinence
but it did seem to help with stress
incontinence decreasing by an average of
61 percent in the yoga group versus only
35 in controls with no significant
changes in urgency incontinence
foreign